<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The elegant combat or, the mutuall entertainement between the two learned and famous Frenchmen Monseiur [sic] Du Moulin and Monseiur [sic] De Balzac Extracted out of the originall, by Robert Codrington master of arts. And dedicated to the truely ennobled Master Anthony Mildemay.</title>
            <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7322.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113614</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848846</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848846</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176714</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12524)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176714)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 643:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The elegant combat or, the mutuall entertainement between the two learned and famous Frenchmen Monseiur [sic] Du Moulin and Monseiur [sic] De Balzac Extracted out of the originall, by Robert Codrington master of arts. And dedicated to the truely ennobled Master Anthony Mildemay.</title>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
                  <author>Codrington, Robert, 1601-1665.</author>
                  <author>Balzac, Jean-Louis Guez, seigneur de, 1597-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Anne Griffin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also issued as part 2 of STC 7321.5. For another translation see STC 7344--STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Venyes at eloquence.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-O⁴.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 7322a on UMI microfilm reel 643..</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176714:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176714:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Elegant Combat OR, THE Mutuall Entertainement between the two learned and famous Frenchmen Monſeiur <hi>Du Moulin</hi> and Monſeiur <hi>De Balzac.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Extracted out of the originall, By <hi>Robert Codrington</hi> Maſter of Arts.</p>
            <p>And dedicated to the truely ennobled Maſter <hi>Anthony Mildemay.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Anne Griffin</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Anne Griffin.</hi> 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176714:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176714:2"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVE LOVER of all good Learning, and the perfect Mirrour of his owne ranke, the moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and the moſt accompliſhed, <hi>Anthony Mildemay,</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F theſe papers liue, it is becauſe they deuote themſelues to you, in whom alone they gratulate the happineſſe of your Family, which is ennobled by ſoe ſafe and ſo pure a Vertue, that as no Enuy dares ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approach it, ſo no Flattery can corrupt it, a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily which hath enioyed the fauour of your
<pb facs="tcp:176714:3"/>Soueraignes by deſcent, and which hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued your Vertues as hereditary as your honours. But becauſe it did appeare to cheape a glory to be abſolute in that Court which the King doth daily crowne with the diuine exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of his Vertues, and where hee is no Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect whoſe practiſe expreſſeth not the loyalty of obedience to ſuch his moſt royall inclinations, it hath beene your Buſineſſe to tranſplant them into remote Kingdomes and Courts, who haue admired the method of his Gouernment by your Diſcourſe, and beleiued it by your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, a Truth which their Jmitation hath illuſtrated, and which the Pirat and the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell hath vnderſtood and beene guilty of it, who taken more by the more victorious ſweetneſſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your Nature, then you were by their inſolence forgate that they were Turkes and made your Deliuerance as famous as your Wiſdome. You haue enioyed by this a reflecting happineſſe, and haue improued our Practice at home, by being
<pb facs="tcp:176714:3"/>ſuch a ſtudied and an elaborate Example a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and teaching diſperſed Nations the Engliſh Vertue, you haue made the World in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to your owne. Theſe are the Garlands which doe crowne your praiſes, which your loue to learning doth perpetuate &amp; aduance as much in excellence as number, but the modeſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of learning being Compendious alwaies in the Panegyriks of her liuing Benefactors doth become to them more abſolute and more iuſt by Death, for Eternity being the Obiect and the End of Learning, their Memory muſt rather be her Subiect then themſelues. But your loue vnto Religion as it is vnbounded, ſo will your Reward be, which hath inuited Bleſsings to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend vpon you, Bleſsings which ſhall raiſe you high as in their Centre from whence they flow, and leauing your Story a mirrour to Poſterity, ſhall giue life vnto your Epitaph, when the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of your Tombe can remember it no more. This I do not preſage, but demonſtrate, for Fame
<pb facs="tcp:176714:4"/>is but the herauld and the voice of Honour, and Jmmortality rather a Debt then a Reward to Vertue. But I forbeare to afflict you with your praiſes, which are therefore the more due, the more vnwilling you are to heare them. Pardon my impoſed Errour, the aſſurance of your Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues did giue vnto my knowledge that it was a ſin to conceale them and my inſufficiency to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe that knowledge hath made my language as guilty as my ſilence. But <hi>I</hi> preſume theſe few leaues deliuered in what forme ſoeuer will be acceptable to you, not for any beauty that this rude hand of mine can lend vnto them, but for the primitiue excellence of their Authors, who meet as admirably in their eloquence as they differ in their ſence. The ſmallnes of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſhall the more ennoble and crowne your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance. The Sea receiueth the ſmalleſt drops with as much acknowledgement as the greateſt Riuers, &amp; the like liberality of entertainment hath renowned the Aſsyrian Monarch, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deerd
<pb facs="tcp:176714:4"/>him more to Immortality then all the Glory of the Eaſt or the Maieſty of his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires could. Be pleaſed to entertaine this with your leaſure and your patience, which ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige mee ere many moneths be expired, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with a larger volume, as deuoted euer to expreſſe my ſelfe,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The conſtant honourer of your Vertues,</hi> R. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176714:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176714:5"/>
            <head>A Letter of Mounſeiur <hi>Du Moulin</hi> to Mounſeiur <hi>De Balzac.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue receiued the booke which out of your fauour it hath pleaſed you to ſend vnto mee, which you could not haue giuen to any Man that did more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme it, or leſſe deſerve it, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I finde my ſelfe one of the moſt vnworthy to come into your remembrance, yet I am one of the firſt that doe extoll your Vertue, by which you have attained to the height of the Art of Eloquence, and drawing the Bridge after you haue with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration left Deſpaire vnto Poſterity. In the deſcription of Eloquence which the Ancients thought to haue no being but in Fancy, you haue made an entire bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and haue demonſtrated that a man of theſe times may out goe them, the force and dexterity of your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hauing exceeded their imagination, you delight
<pb facs="tcp:176714:6"/>the vnderſtanding and inſtruct it, and haue ioyned two things rarely ſociable, beauty with ſolidity. This is one of the belſſings of this Age to have bred a Man that in effect hath ſhewed how farre that Eloquence may goe. But of this I had rather ſpeake to others than your ſelfe, who without affecting praiſe are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to merit it, and which followeth you ſo much the cloſer, by how much the leſſe you ſearch it, ſo that hee muſt borrow your pen who worthily would praiſe it, and I aſſure you that for the exerciſing of it you haue made choice of a ſubiect proportionable to your wit. For as the things done by the King could not bee performed by any other then himſelfe, ſo could not they haue worthily been written by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then by you, you inſult eſpecially on our miſeries, but in that you are not to bee blamed, becauſe you write according to your vnderſtanding, and that without this draught of your pencill the Kings pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture could not bee perfected, whom though God hath imployed to humble vs, yet hath not his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty forgotten our ancient ſeruices, nor is hee ignorant how that the late King his Father of glorious memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry found no refuge in time of his affliction but among our Churches. Would you be offended Sir, if I ſhould ſay, that it ſeemes to me, that God hath preſented you another Subiect worthy of your excellent Wit, that is the proweſſe and the happy ſucceſſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:176714:6"/>King of <hi>Sweden</hi> for ſinee the King whom you haue drawne out in ſo rich colours cannot ſatisfy himſelfe to heare himſelfe but praiſed, you ſhall follow his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations in drawing the portraict of another King that emulates his Vertues, meane while your worke ſhall be to me not only a proofe of your ſufficiency, but alſo a pledge of your Bounty, and ſeeing it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong my other bookes, I ſhall almoſt begin to think my ſelfe ſomebody, becauſe in ſending it to me, you teſtifie that you haue ſome good opinion of me, which ſhall obliege me to wiſh your proſperity and to remaine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble and affectionate ſeruant. <hi>Du Moulin.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176714:7"/>
            <head>The Letter of Mounſeiur <hi>De Balzac</hi> to Mounſeiur <hi>Du Moulin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, There is no modeſty that can reſiſt the praiſes that come from you, and I ſhould diſſemble if I ſhould not acknowledge that I tooke pleaſure to ſuffer my ſelfe to be corrupted by the firſt lines of your letter, but I muſt know my ſelfe a great deale leſſe then I doe to remaine long in that errour; A Man after he hath had a pleaſant dream awaketh, and I ſee well that after you have ſpoken ſo advantageouſly of my labour, you have not vſed all the ſeuerity of your iudgement, fauour you haue done me rather then iuſtice, and have ſought to oblige me though with the hazard of offending truth, your ſelfe being theformoſt you encourage thoſe that are in the race with your hand and voyce, and to perſwade them to follow you, you make them beleeve they
<pb facs="tcp:176714:7"/>ſhall outgoe you. Lo here in good earneſt an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Artifice, and which I had not diſcouered at the firſt bluſh, But whatſoeuer it be, or from what prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple ſoever this glorious approbation comes to me, I doe no leſſe eſteem it then an ambitious man would doe a crowne, and without penetrating into your deſigne I rejoyce in myfortune. It is no ſmal thing Sir, to be beloved of you whom I have alwayes perfectly eſteemed, and haue now a long time marked of the Huguenots party, as an excellent pilot who dares braue a whole fleet out of a Cockeboat, we haue the Right and the Authority, but you haue the Addreſſe and the Stratagems, and are no leſſe confident of your courage then wee are of our cauſe. Certaine it is that thereby you may giue to a Sedition the apparence of a juſt warre, and to a multitude of Mutineeres the face of a well diſciplin'd army, thereby you make pleaſing to many people an opinion that hath loſt the grace of novelty, and although it leaneth towards a downefall, wee muſt confeſſe it hath both linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and complexion in your writings, and that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any man did ſo cunningly couer weakeneſſe or hold vp ruines with finer force
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si Pergamadextrâ</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Defendi poſsint etiam bâc defenſa fuiſſent:</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>The Towne of <hi>Troy</hi> from being made a Graue</l>
                  <l>This arme of thine if any Arme could ſaue.</l>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:176714:8"/>I vſe alwaies this language when there is occaſion to ſpeake of you, nor doe I take any part at all with the paſſions of the vulgar, who conſerue not the liberty of their owne, iudgement, and know neither the faults of their owne nor the vertues of ſtrangers. Forme out of what cloude ſoeuer the Day comes forth, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth beautifull, and I aſſure my ſelfe that at Rome the better part did praiſe <hi>Hanniball,</hi> and none but ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beians ſpoke opprobiouſly of him. For it is a kind of ſacrilege to bereaue whomſoeuer it be of the gifts of God, and if I did not confeſſe that you had receiued much, I ſhould thinke my ſelfe iniurious to him who had given you much, and in a different cauſe ſhould offend our common Benefactor. It is true that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I haue not flattered your party, and haue beene a little moued againſt the Authors of theſe late tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, but hauing obſerued in your bookes that our opinions were agreeable, and that ſubiection due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Soueraigne did make vp a part of that religion which you teach, I thought I might ſpeake with your conſent that which I haue already ſaid, and that in this I was but your ſimple interpreter. Be the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt begotten by the North or by the South, it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually odious to me, and I take not counſaile in what concernes my duty either of England or of Spaine. My humour is not to fight againſt the times, nor to oppoſe my ſelfe againſt things preſent, it is paine, to
<pb facs="tcp:176714:8"/>mee to conceiue onely the Idaea of <hi>Cato</hi> or of <hi>Brutus,</hi> and being to liue vnder the power of another I finde no vettue more conuenient then obedience. If I were a Swiſſe I could be content to be the Kings compere, and would not be his ſubiect nor change my liberty for the beſt maſter in the world. But ſince God hath made me to be borne in chaines I beare them willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſeeing they are neither rude nor heauy I will not mar my teeth in trying how to break them. It ſeemes that Heauen approueth a gouernment which it hath maintained by the ſucceſſion of twelue hundred yeares, an Euil which had ſo long continued might in ſome ſort become lawfull, and if the Age of men bee venerable that of ſtates is holy. Thoſe great ſpirits which I haue deſigned in my worke, and which you haue had of your party ought to haue come in the beginning of the world, to haue giuen lawes to new people, and to haue trauaild in the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of policy. But as it is neceſſary to inuent good things, ſocertainely it is moſt dangerous to goe about to change euen euill ones themſelves. I haue no cruell thoughts Sir but thoſe onely that concerne the cheifes of your party. I treate in a manner as an enemy, and I care not for inſulting on your miſeries, as you ciuilly reproach me, I who haue written that the King ſhould be bleſſed of all the world if after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuppreſt the pride of Rebells he did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult
<pb facs="tcp:176714:9"/>on the misfortune of the afflicted. The perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of thoſe who ſubmit themſelues are in like exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration with me as the deſtroyers of tombes, neither haue I onely pitty of affliction, in ſome ſort I haue it in reuerence. I know that heretofore men conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted places that were ſtricken with thunder, the finger of God was reſpected in the perſon of the miſerable, and great adverſities doe rather worke Religion then receiue reproaches. But ſo to ſtile the good ſucceſſe of the Kings armes were to ſpeake improperly, wee haue all gained in his Victory, all the paine that hath beene impoſed vpon yours hath beene to make you as happy as our ſelues, and they are now poſſeſſors and enioyers of that ſecurity of which they were but amorous &amp; iealous before their townes were taken. Our Prince will put no yoake on the conſciences of his ſubiects, hee will not haue that receiued by force which cannot be well receiued but by perſwaſion, nor vſe thoſe remedies againſt the French which were good againſt the Moores. If the King of Sweden doth ſo vſe his proſperity, and doth not defile ſo pure a Grace by puniſhments and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, I promiſe you to doe that which you haue deſired of me, and to imploy all my Art and Vtenſils to erect him a ſtatue. This is iuſt to touch my incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to pray me to praiſe that prince, when ſhould all the Crownes which are imbroidered on his Scarfe
<pb facs="tcp:176714:9"/>bee changed into ſo many kingdomes, they would not be ſufficient (me thinks) to recompence ſo rare a Vertue or to imploy ſo vaſt a Spirit. As I expect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Greatneſſe from his valour, ſo I hope for nothing but Goodneſſe from his Vertue. And although ſome haue declared in Spaine that hee is the very AntiChriſt, yet I am neither ſo deuout to beleeue that newes, nor ſo fearefull to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid thereof. Onely I ſay vnto Scrupulous Men who aske mee thereabouts, that in the meane time our King hath there a Second that ſerues him well and that no Man could preſent vnto the houſe of Auſtria a Demurre that could di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert him more from ſtudying on our affaires. Sir, I will paſſe noe farther, Better it is to ſtand at the portall of a holy place then to enter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into being vnprepared. Beſides that this diſcourſe is already long enough for the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Acquaintance. Pardon (if you pleaſe) the Contentment which I haue in entertaining you, which is the cauſe that I haue forgotten both your buſineſſe and my Cuſtome which is not to preach with my friends, but you haue giuen mee the Text which I haue treated on and I beleeue that you hauing ſuddainly ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the bottome of my heart, and I not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling
<pb facs="tcp:176714:10"/>with you my affections; you wil hereafter take Confidence in my freedome; with which I proteſt vnto you moſt ſolemnely that I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble and affectionate ſeruant. <hi>De Balzac.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176714:10"/>
            <head>An anſwer of Monſeiur <hi>DuMoulin</hi> to the letter of Monſeiur <hi>De Balzac.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had ere now anſwered your letters if they had beene in my Poſſeſſion, but they haue along time runne vp and down the towne euery one deſiring to take a Copy thereof, and from the towne they haue walked to the Villages from whence the peſtilence hath remoued us, for albeit that in all your writings there ſhine the force and liuelineſſe of your Spirit ſeaſoned with Grace and Sweetneſſe, tye in theſe letters you haue excell'd your ſelfe, ſo ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate is the ſtile, and the Conceptions ſtrong and pleaſing, that all here gliſters: neither doth the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hinder the cleereneſſe of it, wherein you are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fferent from many of theſe times who take delight to
<pb facs="tcp:176714:11"/>dabble in the inke, and amongſt plenty of thornes haue but little light, like that of a Gloworme ſhining out of a Buſh, wherefore in reiecting the praiſes that I haue giuen your quill, you ſhew in earneſt how much you doe deſerue them, for you reiect the title of eloquent with ſo much eloquence, as it ſeemes that you haue taken a taske vpon you to ſhew that your Modeſty is vniuſt, and to accuſe me for not hauing praiſed you enough, you muſt change your ſtile if you would bee beleeued, and muſt become barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the end you may perſwade. It would very ill become me to reply vpon all points of your letter, I will not enter into that liſt with you, the ſcope of my writings being not to ſtroke the eare but to ſtrike the Conſcience: This is their preuiledge that write for true Doctrine, that incongruities paſſe oftentimes for elegancies, and that Barbariſme is ſociable with Truth. For as blew and red flowers among the Corne doe delight the eye but diſaduantage the harueſt, ſo ornaments among good doctrine doe diminiſh the fruit of the teaching, and doe cauſe that inſteed of of teaching matters wee are ſtaid at words, and doe weigh periods, theſe flowers muſt fall before the fruites come on, and groſſer termes doe oftentimes giue a deeper impreſſion. And it being neceſſary in ſuch matters to vſe ſometimes ſtrong reprehenſions; to bring hither the flowers of eloquence, were as if
<pb facs="tcp:176714:11"/>we ſhould ſcourge our children with a noſegay. It is for falſe religions to borrow theſe ornaments, as in their Temples and Ceremonies they will haue ſplendor, ſo they require a ſwollne and an artificiall language, like vnto a Woman ſparkling with Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds whoſe eyes are blind, which Sir, I ſay to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to thoſe offenſiue praiſes which you too liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſtow vpon mee, praiſing mee in that I haue a Grace to lye, ſaying that I defend a bad cauſe with dexterity and Stratagems, without right and without Authority, and that I maintaine an opinion which hath loſt the grace of nouelty, and for the height of all my praiſes, you ſay that I would be fit to giue a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition the apparence of a iuſt warre, which dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of ſeducing you place amongſt the gifts of God, which you ſay you haue in great eſteeme, ſo with a double artifice you pricke me as you tickle me, and lift mee vp a ſpectacle on high after you haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmutched and deformed mee. Pardon mee Sir if I tell you that there is no blame which is not more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable then theſe praiſes, to bring more Art and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry to defend Error ſerueth to no other end but to goe to hell with a better Grace, and to ſweeten poiſon to deſtroy both himſelfe and others with more dexterity. It were better a thouſand times for ſuch a Man to be dumbe then ſo vnhappily eloquent, and to bee the moſt bruitiſh amongſt men then to
<pb facs="tcp:176714:12"/>haue ſuch an ingenious peruerſeneſſe. This is ill ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of meaſures, to place a fraudulent Eloquence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the gifts of God. It is rather the Deuill who whets the tongue and pen of ſuch a Man, and lends him his armes to make warre againſt God. In briefe you haue heapt on mee thoſe praiſes which <hi>Homer</hi> giues to <hi>Paris,</hi> prayſing the beauty of his lockes but making him to bee the ruine of his Country. Now that if on our ſide there were Benifices, Riches, and Penſions, you might haue ſome Colour to thinke that a ſpirit deſirous to appeare had beene drawne by theſe allurements to defend an euill cauſe, but Pouerty and Reproach being the Cognizance of our Profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion, to bee wicked for nothing would be with the loſſe of piety to loſe common Sence. And whereas you ſay that our Religion hath loſt the grace of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelty, I ſay that it is impoſſible it ſhould looſe that which it neuer had, but if it were or had beene new, this ſhould not haue beene a Grace vnto it but a Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh. Nouelty may giue ſome grace vnto Sallets or Apparell, but not to the Doctrine of Saluation: that were good newes for Italy, where the new Saints doe make the old ones looſe their Credit, and for the church of Rome in which the Pope doth vaunt of his power to change that which God hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his word, and that he can make new Articles of Faith, who not being able to ſay with Saint <hi>Peter</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:176714:12"/>Gold and Siluer I haue none, vſeth his ſhip to traffick; making a noiſe with the keyes, whoſe locks he hath changed. From this head a defluxion is fallen on the Body of the Clergy, who ſet vp their Banke in the Temple, and abandoning the <hi>Dominicall letter,</hi> are altogether addicted to the <hi>goldennu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber,</hi> From whence it comes to paſſe that all is put to ſale, euen God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and the remiſſion of ſinnes, and that priuate Maſſes are not ſaid but for thoſe who haue contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Church, the wit of auarice digging euen into Sepulchers, ſo that a rich Man cannot goe cheape into his Graue. And there can be no greater change then of a ſpirituall to make a temporall Monarchy, but our Religion is the true and ancient Chriſtianity, onely new in this, that it reiecteth all nouelty, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem eth doctrine new that is not from the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; It being the heauenly Truth which the Son of God brought into the world, the violence of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked people haue no more power againſt it then the Winds haue power to change the beames of the Sunne. This is it, why I make my prediction quite contrary to yours, and inſtead of the declining which you ſpeake of I aſſure my ſelfe that it wil flouriſh and chaſe away the darkeneſſe of this Age by the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it. And I wonder how you can delude your ſelfe with ſuch a hope, in a time wherein our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on receiueth ſo great Increaſe in the low Countreyes
<pb facs="tcp:176714:13"/>and in Germany, and wherein the Greeke Churches doe range themſelues vnder our Confeſſion, being drawne thereunto by the euidence of the Truth. This without doubt is one of the praiſes which you reſerue for the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> to haue contributed to ſo good a Worke, of whom beſides his Valour and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe you will aduance his Clemency, and for this that in places conquered he hath vſed no violence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Roman Clergy, but letteth euen the Ieſuites themſelues alone, although they teach that it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to kill Kings, and that many parricides haue come out of their ſchooles, who hauing lately called this King Anti Chriſt doe now in their Colleges make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations to his praiſe. And if our Churches in France doe ſuffer any Diminution, this proceeds not from the Cauſe of the contrary party, but from the Auarice of ſome of our Nobility who wound vs in giuing eare to that TIBIDABO which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill propounded to the Sonne of God, for there are found of thoſewho are alwaies armed againſtiron, but not againſt ſiluer, and in this golden Age a bag of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolls is of great weight, &amp; being put into the balance doth often times ouerweigh the Conſcience. But the Church is no more weakned by that, then a Mans body is by hauing vomited a worme or ſpit forth ſome filthineſſe. So Pride, Vanity, and Auarice are more conueniently lodged in the temples of Idols
<pb facs="tcp:176714:13"/>then in the houſe of God. True it is that thoſe of your party do talke of our Religion with great Contempt as of a deſperate Cauſe which notwithſtanding from the loweſt is often mounted vp on high: they ſpeake of vs, as if we intended to mine the Alpes with a pin or pierce a Lyon with a feſtraw. They blacke vs ouer with iniuries doing as the enemies of the Goſpell did of old who clad the Martirs in the skins of wilde beaſts to animate the dogges to teare them, for they transforme vs into monſters to prouoke the people againſt vs, but the ſonne of God hath prepared vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this reproach, and he himſelfe hath paſſed by the like proofes. I doe rely vpon your goodneſſe and your Wiſdome that you will ſupport me if I be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible on this ſide, for you are too cleare ſighted not to diſcerne the weakeneſſe of your Cauſe, hauing a long time liued at Rome from whence with the examples of vices came the deciſions of the Faith; where the Iewes, enemies of the name of Chriſt doe liue in peace, but the Chriſtians &amp; the faithfull are burned; where in the time of Lent the Shambles are ſhut and the Stewes are open; where the Penitents whip themſelues in publike for the ſins of others; where is exerciſed a marchandiſe of Annats, of benifices, of diſpenſations, and pardons: and I remember that I have reade in one of your letters that it is excellent good ſinning there, and that you diſtinguiſh the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb facs="tcp:176714:14"/>religion from the Popes Court, for feare the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the one ſhould not ſtirre vp an euill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of the other, although that this Court doth rule religion. A ſpirit excellent as yours ſhould not ſuffer it ſelfe to bee inknarled with ſuch ſenſeleſſe opinions. But you haue a more delieate religion then that which the vulgar do beleeue, or your Church doth inſtitute, nor doe you faſten vpon any thing which is not agreeable to your humour. I make no doubt but you ſcorne the hypocondriacall deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe who adore bones, who kiſſing and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling Images and toſſing up and downe their hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed graines, doe make their prayers by tale in words they vnderſtand not. Without doubt you doe not thinke it good that Seruice ſhould be ſaid in an vnknowne tongue as if God were become barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to Men, or as if the Pope had forbidden God to ſpeake in French; you haue ſeene at Rome many Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars where the Pope hath ſet vp pardons for a 100 and 200 thouſand yeares with as many quaran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, and power to draw a ſoule out of purgatory; you haue ſeene there the madneſſe of the people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming two or three hundred miles to a Iubily to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the remiſſion of their ſins which God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vs at home by the preaching of the Goſpell; nor are you ignorant out of what ſtocke the Pope drawes this his liberality; for he heapes vp the ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance
<pb facs="tcp:176714:14"/>of Faſtings, whippings, pilgrimages of Saints and Monkes, and conuerts the ſame into pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the ſins of others. When at Rome you did refreſh your chamber with a Gale ſufficient to driue a Ship, and did mount into your Caroach onely, to croſſe a ſtreet, you had not then the leiſure to ſtudie theſe ſuperſtitions. But if you had then the Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to take the miſſall, and therein to read the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels and the Rubricks which doe prouide againſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences in caſe the winde ſhould carry away their God, or the Rats ſhould haue eaten <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> or the Prieſt ſhould vomit him vp, you would excuſe vs and ſay, certainely it is no maruaile if this poore people do finde theſe things of ſo hard digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ill agreeing with the maieſtie of the Sonne of God. On two points principally we inſiſt, namely on the Succeſſion of the Pope into the Apoſtleſhip, and on the primacy of S. <hi>Peter:</hi> and we could neuer yet obtaine that any Man would ſhew vs the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of theſe two things out of the word of God. But enough of theſe matters, from which I would haue abſtained if you had not puſhed me forward. I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the reſt of your letters. Obedience vnto So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes is a thing both iuſt and neceſſary. To find in our owne Religion or in that of the Kings occaſions of Rebellion is to raiſe vp tumults to defend religion by courſes condemned by Religion it ſelfe, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:176714:15"/>neceſſitated in their owne particular affaires, doe hope to finde eaſe by moouing the fiſhpoole and to ſaue themſelues in the middeſt of Confuſion. The Cauſe of God was neuer aduanced that way. <hi>Moſes</hi> had power to ſtrike Egypt and their King with great plagues, yet would he neuer draw the Iſraelites out of Egypt without the permiſſion of their King. I am of opinion that in Ciuill Cauſes it is more expedient for the people to haue a bad maſter then to haue none at all; how much more hauing a good and clement King are wee obliged to be faithfull to him, who in pardoning vs hath not done as they doe who help forward their clemency by diſdaine, eſteeming him that hath offended them vnworthy of their choller, but hee hath followed his naturall inclination which hath carried him not only to pardon but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit alſo, ſo that to be conquered by him is profitable. Furthermore I haue alwaies beleeued that there is no worſe eſtate then Anarchy, in which euery one is a ſlaue becauſe euery one is a maſter and where the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of liberty is the Cauſe of Slauery. For this liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bringeth licence, and licence confuſion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion ſlauery. As the hand would be an vnproper inſtrument, were the fingers all of an equall length, So a multitude of equall perſons moue not without inconuenience; your <hi>maxime</hi> that it is dangerous to change euill lawes is true out of the buſineſſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.
<pb facs="tcp:176714:15"/>To ſubiect a Mans ſelfe by docility vnto lawes which lead unto hell, is to breake the lawes of God, and ſuch who haue made thoſe lawes ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect before God, thoſe who obey them. But where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to bee conſidered but the loſſe of goods and life, it is better to vndergoe that vniuſt yoake then to bee exempted from it by troubling the publike peace by rebellion againſt the Soueraigne, for the force of humane lawes doth not conſiſt in this that they are iuſt, but in that they are lawes, and are made by them who haue Authority, and albeit they haue ſomething of vniuſt in them, yet it is iuſt to obey them. There are to bee found Eſtates who haue a long time liued in peace and proſperity vnder vniuſt Lawes well obſerued, and others liuing vnder iuſt Lawes but ill obſerued haue fallen into ruine and confuſion. This peace and proſperity will bee all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes found more durable in a Monarchy than in any other forme of State, for it is the onely ciuill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement which imitates the gouernement of the vniuerſall World, where there is but one Maſter, and all other States when they are much growne muſt of neceſſity come vnto it. But of Monarchies ſubſiſting at this day, this of France hath the preheminence in Antiquity and good Lawes: the moouing humour of our nation &amp; inclined to change is a cleere proofe that the State is well compoſed, for it had long ſince
<pb facs="tcp:176714:16"/>ouerturned the State, if the Pillars were not firme, and the building well compacted. Being borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Monarchy wee deſire the proſperity of it, and that the crowne of our King may be like the crowne of Egges which daily doth increaſe by Age. If our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion were generally receiued in France, the Kings Maieſtie ſhould bee more exalted and his power ſhould the more enlarge it ſelfe. For the Pope ſhould no more pretend to haue power ouer the life and the Crowne of our Kings, and ſhould vaunt no more that hee might depoſe them, there ſhould not in France bee any more iuſtice than that of the Kings. Cauſes bred on this ſide the Alpes ſhould not be called ouer to Rome. The Clergie ſhould bee ſubiect to Ciuill Lawes and ſhould bee tryable before the Kings Iudges. The Kingdome ſhould no more bee exhauſted of money that goes to Rome for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nats, diſpenſations, and pardons. So many Lands poſſeſſed by the Clergy and thereby fallen into mortmaine ſhould owe vnto the King the ſame ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices and duties which other Lands doe which are poſſeſt by the Nobility. In briefe I dare ſay that the principall reaſon of the hatred which men beare to vs is becauſe we defend by the Word of God the right of our Kings againſt the vſurpation of the Popes, who make them kiſſe their pantofles and vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of penance doe impoſe vpon them corporall
<pb facs="tcp:176714:16"/>puniſhments. But this is our vnhappineſſe that as the holy Scripture is a booke which is hid from Kings, ſo in that which concernes the liberty and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependance of their Crownes, they learne nothing but from them whom the Pope holds bound by the belly. But this is too much. The pleaſure which I take in entertaining you makes mee forget that I write an Epiſtle and not a booke, and hath carried me beyond my limits: that clauſe wherein you ſay that I would giue vnto a ſedition the apparence of a iuſt warre hath urged me to take ſome kind of reuenge which hath bin this, to tire you with the length of my letters; yet it ſhall not hinder mee from admiring the beauty and the force of your wit. I honour the guifts of God whereſoeuer they bee found, on the other ſide alſo, I hope that this little ſharpenes which I haue vſed ſhall not depriue him of your fauours who honours you and who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble and affectionate ſeruant. <hi>Du Moulin.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
